<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Question 23</title>
        <author ref="#Holcot">Holcot</author>
        <editor>Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Question 23</title>
          <date when="2018-09-13">September 13, 2018</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="pembroke236">Pembroke 236</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2018-09-13" who="#JW" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="include-list">
        <xi:include href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-lists/master/workscited.xml" xpointer="worksCited"/>
        <xi:include href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-lists/master/Prosopography.xml" xpointer="prosopography"/>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="154-v"/><cb ed="#P" n="b"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521">
        <head xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-Hd1e4126">Question 23</head>
        <head xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-Hd1e4129" type="question-title">
          Whether quality admits of a greater or lesser degree
        </head>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e4132">
          Whether quality admits of a greater or lesser degree.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e4141">
          I respond 
          that this proposition should be distinguished 
          according to the composed and divided sense. 
          The composite sense is impossible 
          because no quality takes a greater and lesser at the same time.
          The divided sense is true 
          and this is with respect to the logic of the question. 
          With respect the matter he <!-- he/it/who?? --> puts 
          that color has some latitude
          Nevertheless, <mentioned>that color has latitude</mentioned> 
          is able to be understood in two ways.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e139">
          In one mode thus 
          that it does not really have distinct intermediates, 
          just as is true about time and motion 
          because an hour and a year are not really distinguished 
          just as Socrates in the forum and Socrates in the theater 
          are not really distinguished.
          But when it is said that time has parts, 
          one of which is day and another is year or hour, 
          these propositions ought to be understood thus, 
          hour is part of day and this thing, 
          as it is an hour, 
          lasts less than an a day or a year. 
          Or it is able to be explained thus,
          the following proposition is true longer <mentioned>in this region the heavens are day</mentioned> 
          than this proposition <mentioned>in the same region the heavens are now in the ninth hour</mentioned>. 
          And in this way it should be conceded 
          that time has intermediaries.
          And then not in another sense unless this:
          <mentioned>the heavens, as it is hour, does not thus last longer, 
          just as the heavens, as it is a year or double time to a year or an hour</mentioned>. 
          And it is in the same way concerning the latitude of heat,
          for the same thing is the latitude of heat and heat. 
          And the latitude of heat has parts, 
          just as time 
          because the same heat, as it is in the process of changing 
          is called 'latitude', and when it is changed 
          is called <mentioned>heat</mentioned> and not <mentioned>latitude</mentioned>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e200">
          In another mode, 
          having really distinct intermediaries 
          could be to be conceded or be understood intensively, 
          and this sense beckons and denies. <!-- unsure of "innuit" and translation -->
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e4237">
          In a third mode, 
          it is possible for having distinct intermediaries 
          to be understood extensively
          according to the intermediaries of the subject, 
          and thus he <!-- he?? who? --> concedes that both time and motion have 
          really distinct intermediaries, 
          just the heavens themselves have 
          because there is not a latitude 
          except the heat itself.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e4255">
          I respond to the first argument that, 
          if fire in the highest degree ought to generate from water 
          fire in the highest degree, 
          it should not be imagined that 
          continuously in the beginning of the action of fire 
          the latitude of heat is led into water. 
          Rather there is a successive corruption of the water. 
          and it does not lead some heat of fire 
          nor the form of fire before an ultimate instant of corruption of water, 
          and then immediately will lead to the highest fire and highest color.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e4294">
          <pb ed="#P" n="155-r"/>
          <cb ed="#P" n="a"/>
          Again, 
          in solving the second principale argument, 
          where he <!-- he/it? who? --> inquires,
          whether contraries at the same time are coextended in the same subject, 
          he holds that this is not so 
          on account of many arguments, 
          saying that, when fire is generated from water, 
          it should not be imagined it is immediately corrupted 
          and then fire would be generated and intended successively,
          nor that through the intermediary of time in which 
          the matter of water will be changed is the whole water successively corrupted, 
          and in another intermediary the form of fire. 
          Rather water is successively corrupted and the form of fire and its heat 
          will be immediately generated 
          such that it is that heat is not generated before the entire cold is corrupted, 
          nevertheless this heat through which water is called hot is 
          the same thing with the coldness of water, 
          and coldness removed from water is accidental heat. 
          Whence there are not hot things of the same species 
          because accidental heat of water is of a different species 
          than the heat of fire and of the sames species with the cold of water, 
          and therefore water made hot returns to coldness 
          without an extrinsic agent. 
          Whence properly it does not change itself 
          because alteration is properly is a remission of a form
          contrary to the form of the agent. Whence this hotness, 
          when it becomes weaker does not remit hotness 
          but is intended, 
          and the reason is because
          this hotness is essentially coldness 
          and accidentally hot.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e4377">
          Against, 
          according to the same person, 
          corruption of a natural thing is not contrary to its generation 
          through the same degrees, 
          but generation of fire from water will be from the 
          contrary corruption of the form of water and its coldness,
          and the generation of water from that will be from successive corruption 
          in the latitude of fire and its hotness, 
          and water its coldness will immediately be generated,
          and this it is saved what is accept the first instant of a permanent thing in being 
          and thus the last,
          and the quality of motion is denoted from a prior passion 
          according to the imagination of the <name>Commentator</name> in book 8 of the Physics, 
          in comment 69. 
          However, that heat in water is essentially coldness, 
          he proves thus, 
          through a sign
          because heat in water remits hotness equally 
          when causing with water. 
          But the consequence is not because 
          some hotness would remit the hotness of the same species.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e4440">
          But if is said that, 
          if hotness in water is essentially coldness, 
          why does it not represent the feeling of coldness 
          but instead the feeling of hotness?
          He responds that, 
          just as white posited by something removed through a removed intension represents 
          blackness to sight or to the corporal medium, 
          so the coldness of water significantly remitted 
          represents hotness.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="beq3sc-d1e521-d1e4451">
          Note that the same heat is able to be more intense
          than it already is without the addition of another 
          because suppose God makes two intermediaries of a heat 
          coextending at the same time in the same place, 
          therefore it is twice as intense as before. 
          But he does not argue against this 
          because in this way the heat of Christ will be more intense 
          than the heat of some other 
          because his intermediary is in the same place 
          the intermediary of the others, 
          and thus into infinity. 
          It is said that this is not to the proposed 
          because the heat of Christ in the sacrament is not 
          there locally nor situationally, therefore etc.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>